You know the feeling you get
when you learn something new
about a health problem
you’ve been trying to reverse?
Maybe high blood pressure,
diabetes, or heart disease.
Well, there’s nothing I like better
than bringing you the information
that will help you do just that.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we deal with pain:
chronic, debilitating pain.
And we look at how anti-
inflammatory diets can be effective
in alleviating chronic
pain syndromes.
Fibromyalgia is a common disorder
whose cardinal manifestation
is chronic, widespread pain.
Well, not so common, affecting
2 to 4% of the population
though probably more like
2%, and especially women.
For decades, some medical
professionals dismissed fibromyalgia
as all in people’s heads, but this
outdated view has been refuted
by more recent research
characterizing it as a disorder
of pain regulation and sensitization.
Brain imaging studies have shown
several perturbations of pain
processing and regulation
that amplify pain
in people with the condition.
Twin studies have shown that about
half of fibromyalgia is genetic,
but the other half we
can do something about.
There are lots of drugs with
lots of side effects to help
with some of the symptoms, but
what about lifestyle approaches?
Engagement in regular
physical activity is considered
imperative for effective
management of ﬁbromyalgia.
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized clinical
trials on the
effectiveness of therapeutic
exercise in fibromyalgia
found that both aerobic
and resistance exercises
are effective ways of reducing pain
and improving global well-being
in people with fibromyalgia.
Patients may worry and
perceive that exercise
will worsen their pain and fatigue,
and so you have to start slow and
work your way up as tolerated,
with the goal of eventually
achieving 30 to 60 minutes
of moderate intensity aerobic
exercise in addition to
muscle strengthening exercises
(1 to 3 sets of 8–11 exercises,
8–10 repetitions with
a load of about 7 pounds
or 45% of the max you can lift.
But what about dietary
interventions in terms of
dialing down the pain sensitivity?
Well, what causes it in the
first place? Inflammation.
During the inﬂammatory response,
pain receptors are activated,
and chronic inflammation,
can cause chronic activation,
which may cause chronic
pain, due to this prolonged
hypersensitization
of pain pathways.
No wonder, then, that
a pro-inﬂammatory diet
was found to be associated
with pain hypersensitivity
in patients with
fibromyalgia syndrome.
Exactly which foods
are pro-inflammatory
and which foods
are anti-inflammatory?
Check out those twin videos,
but broadly speaking
components of processed
foods and animal products,
such as saturated fat,
trans fat, and cholesterol,
were found to be
pro-inflammatory,
while constituents
of whole plant foods,
such as fiber and phytonutrients,
were strongly anti-inflammatory.
The intake of dietary fiber,
found concentrated in
only one place—
whole plant foods—
is fundamental to reducing not
only the risk of abdominal pain
but also muscle and joint pain,
we think because of these
short chain fatty acids
that our good gut bugs
produce when we eat fiber.
These short chain fatty acids
are important mediators of pain,
fundamentally because
they modulate inﬂammation.
So having a lot of fiber-feeding
bugs in your colon is like
carrying around your own anti-
inflammatory compound factory.
But to cultivate them you actually
have to eat the
foods that feed them.
And in terms of phytonutrients,
plant-derived polyphenols
are widely acknowledged to also
act as anti-inﬂammatory substances.
Here’s some foods packed with
anti-pain pathway nutrients:
berries, greens, citrus, nuts,
spices like turmeric and ginger,
edamame, and green tea.
That’s why you can do randomized,
double-blind crossover trials
showing that about three cups
worth of strawberries a day
can significantly improve
pain and inflammation.
If that’s what a
single plant can do,
what about a diet chock
full of plant foods?
Put people on a strictly
plant-based diet rich in
fresh fruits and vegetables, whole
grains and various legumes,
which are beans, split peas,
chickpeas, and lentils,
as well as nuts and
seeds, and you can drop
C-reactive protein
levels 33% in 3 weeks,
which is a leading blood marker
of systemic inflammation.
But does that translate
into less pain?
And the answer is yes, when it
comes to migraine headaches.
Yes when it comes
to painful periods.
A signiﬁcant reduction in menstrual
pain, duration of pain, intensity
in addition to
premenstrual symptoms.
In fact even just a
single plant, cinnamon,
about a third of a teaspoon three
times a day during your period
can help, though it doesn’t
work as well as ibuprofen.
Ginger powder,
on the other hand—
ground ginger – has been found
to be comparable to
ibuprofen in relieving pain
in women with painful cramps.
Whole-food plant-based
diets also alleviate
the symptoms of osteoarthritis.
Several studies have shown
improvements in rheumatoid arthritis
symptoms with diets
excluding animal products,
though it may be just
as much a function of
increasing the quantity
of healthy plant foods.
But it’s not just because plant-
based diets are so effective
in causing weight loss,
even at the same weight
there’s an improvement
in rheumatoid arthritis
from more plant-based diets.
And plant-based diets can also
alleviate fibromyalgia symptoms.
This is the latest study,
which enrolled anyone
with chronic musculoskeletal
pain, fibromyalgia or not.
Yes, diets high in animal proteins
and fats have been linked to
chronic pain and inﬂammation,
while plant-based diets
produce anti-inﬂammatory responses.
So, did it actually work when
put to the test for pain?
Yes.
Consumption of a
plant-based diet produced
positive improvements
in chronic pain and function.
How much?
Well, a minimally clinically
important diﬀerence in
chronic musculoskeletal
pain is 1 point on the
Numeric Pain Rating Scale,
which is just a scale of 1 to 10,
on how much pain you’re feeling.
And on the plant-based diet
perceived pain
decreased an average of
three points on
a 10-point scale,
from an average of 5 or
6 out of 10 down to 2.
Now, unlike most of prior studies
there was no control group,
but what’s the downside of
giving healthier eating a try?
In fact, those with chronic pain
are more likely to be overweight
and have nutrition-related maladies
such as high blood pressure,
diabetes, and heart disease
all of which can be prevented,
arrested, and in some
cases even reversed
with a healthy-enough
plant-based diet.
So, any pain benefit is just
icing on the cake of health.
Uh...scratch that.
How about...
the dollop of guacamole
on your bean burrito.
In our next story,
we look at how apple peels can
help those with chronic joint pain.
Regular apple intake is associated
with all sorts of good
things, like living longer,
particularly a lower risk
of dying from cancer.
Here’s the survival
curve of elderly women
who don’t eat an apple a day.
Ten years out,
nearly a quarter died,
and 15 years out,
nearly half were gone.
But, those who average like
a half an apple a day
didn’t drop off as fast,
and those eating an apple a day—
more than 3 and a half ounces—
like a cup of apple slices,
stayed around even longer.
Yeah, but maybe people who eat apples
every day just happen to practice
other healthy behaviors
like exercising more, or not smoking,
and that’s really why they’re living longer.
Well, they controlled for most of that–
obesity, smoking status,
poverty, diseases, exercise—
so as to compare apples
to apples (so to speak).
But, what they didn’t control for
was an otherwise healthier diet.
Studies show that those who regularly
eat apples have higher intakes
of not just nutrients like
fiber, found in the apples,
but they’re eating less added sugar,
less saturated fat—in other words,
they’re eating overall healthier diets;
and so, no wonder
apple eaters live longer.
But is apple eating just
a marker for healthy eating,
or is there something about
the apples themselves that’s beneficial?
You don’t know, until...
you put it to the test.
There are all sorts of fun studies
like this, where subjects were randomly
assigned in the morning to nothing,
a caffeinated energy drink,
black coffee, or an apple,
given that athletes use a variety
of common strategies to stimulate
arousal, cognition, and performance
before their morning training.
Did the apple hold its weight?
Yes, appearing to work just as well
as the caffeinated beverages.
The problem with these
kinds of studies though,
is they’re not blinded.
Those in the apple group knew
they were eating an apple,
and so, there may have been
this expectation bias,
placebo effect, that
made them unconsciously
give that extra bit of
effort in the testing
and skew the results.
You just can’t stuff a
whole apple into a pill.
That’s why researchers, instead,
test specific extracted apple components;
so, they can perform a double-blind
placebo controlled study,
where half get the fruit elements,
half get the sugar pill,
and you don’t know until
the end who got which.
The problem there, though, is that
you’re no longer dealing
with a whole food,
removing the symphony of interactions
between the thousands of phytonutrients
in the whole apple.
Most of these special nutrients
are concentrated in the peel, though.
Instead of just dumping millions
of pounds of nutrition in the trash,
why couldn’t researchers
just dry and powder the peels
into opaque capsules to disguise them
and then run blinded studies with that?
Even just a small amount could greatly
increase phytochemical content
and antioxidant activity.
The meat industry got the memo:
dried apple peel powder decreases microbial
expansion in meat and protects against
carcinogen production when you cook it.
And, one of the carcinogens formed
during the grilling of meat
is a beta carboline alkaloid, a neurotoxin,
which may be contributing to the
development of neurological diseases,
like Parkinson’s.
I did a video about it awhile ago.
Uncooked meat doesn’t have any;
the neurotoxin is formed
when you cook it,
but you can cut the levels in half
by first marinating the meat
with dried apple peel powder.
And also cuts down on the amount of
fecal contamination bacteria in the meat.
Apple peels can also inhibit the formation
of genotoxic, DNA-damaging,
heterocyclic amines,
cutting the levels of these
cooked meat carcinogens
by up to more than half.
In view of the risks
associated with consuming
these cancer causing
compounds in meat,
there is a need to reduce exposure
by blocking HCA formation,
such as by adding apple powder
during the cooking of meats
to help prevent their production.
I mean, I can’t think of any other
way to reduce exposure. (mocking)
What about consuming apple peels directly?
Dried apple peel powder was found
to exhibit powerful anti-inflammatory
and antioxidant action,
but this was in mice.
Does it have anti-inflammatory
properties in people?
You don’t know...
until you put it to the test.
A dozen folks with moderate loss of joint
range of motion and
associated chronic pain
were given a spoonful
of dried apple peels
a day for 12 weeks,
and pain scores dropped
month after month,
and the range of motion improved
in their neck, shoulders, back, and hips.
Conclusion: consumption of
dried apple peel powder
was associated with improved
joint function and pain reduction.
Why just “associated”?
Because there was no control group;
so, they might have all been
just getting better on their own,
or it could have been a placebo effect.
But hey, why not give apple peels a try,
by eating more apples.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Stay tuned for December 5, 2023
for the launch of my new one,
How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.